"Benefits and Side Effects of the Pneumonia Vaccine"
Vaccines are considered
one of the greatest
public health achievements
of the last century,
having eradicated smallpox,
a scourge that killed
hundreds of millions of people,
and greatly reducing
other major diseases,
such as measles and polio.
To this day,
vaccines are estimated
to save millions of lives
a year.
More than 90 percent
of U.S. children
get common
childhood vaccinations,
such as polio or their measles,
mumps, and rubella shot,
but most adults fail
to get their full complement
of recommended
adult vaccinations.
Assuming you got
all your childhood vaccinations,
and aside from
any emergent pandemic needs,
the CDC recommends
all healthy adults
get annual flu shots,
tetanus boosters
every ten years,
though the World Health
Organization
doesn't think
this is necessary,
shingles vaccination
at age 50,
and pneumonia vaccine
at age 65.
Certain groups need others,
such as a hepatitis B series
for healthcare workers
or men who have sex with men.
Ask your medical professional
for a personalized schedule.
How safe are vaccines?
In a systematic review
and meta-analysis,
the RAND Corporation screened
more than 50,000 citations
and concluded
that routine vaccinations
can be considered safe,
with only rare
serious adverse effects,
such as severe
allergic reactions,
in 1 to 10 in a million,
and transient autoimmune
syndromes Guillain-Barré
and immune
thrombocytopenic purpura
in 1 to 3 in a million,
and 10 to 30 in a million
for flu shots and MMR vaccines,
respectively.
Of course, any adverse effects
should be weighed against
any protective effects
that vaccines may provide.
In my last video,
I talked about the effectiveness
of flu vaccines.
What about pneumonia vaccines?
"Pneumonia may well be called
the friend of the aged,"
wrote the "Father
of Modern Medicine,"
Sir William Osler,
over a hundred years ago
in 1898.
"Taken off by it
in an acute, short,
not often painful illness,
the old man escapes those
'cold gradations of decay'
so distressing to himself
and to his friends."
The thought
was that pneumonia
mercifully killed those
who would soon die anyway
from potentially a more
protracted, painful illness.
But, these days,
healthy older adults
hospitalized for pneumonia
are not significantly
more likely to die
in the subsequent two years
than younger adults
in the same situation.
Because of comorbidities
at older ages, though,
pneumonia is the fourth leading
cause of death in the world
and the ninth leading cause
in the United States.
The most common cause of
community-acquired pneumonia,
as opposed to hospital-acquired,
is a bacteria
known as pneumococcus,
or Streptococcus pneumoniae.
In addition to pneumonia,
pneumococcus can cause
inner ear infections,
sinusitis, or pinkeye.
It gets serious when it starts
to invade the bloodstream,
which can result in meningitis,
infection of the brain;
endocarditis,
infection of the heart valves;
or sepsis, a life-threatening
organ dysfunction
caused by blood poisoning.
Thankfully, we have vaccines
against pneumococcus.
The first was developed
over a century ago,
but they fell out of favor
after penicillin was discovered,
thinking antibiotics
would eliminate the threat.
Unfortunately,
these days up to 40 percent
of these kind
of streptococcal infections
are resistant
to at least one antibiotic,
and despite our miracle drugs,
mortality rates
of invasive pneumococcus
in the elderly remain
around 15 to 30 percent.
However,
randomized controlled trials
have found
that pneumococcus vaccines
reduce the risk
of those 65 and older
getting pneumococcal pneumonia
by 64 percent,
and, even more importantly,
your risk of invasive
pneumococcal disease
by 73 percent.
Like the flu vaccine,
population studies have found
that pneumonia vaccines
can reduce the risk
of both heart attacks
and the overall risk of dying,
but unlike flu vaccines,
there aren't randomized
controlled trials
to confirm
these bonus benefits.